
===== PDF PAGE 7 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
2 
B. IMPORTANT INFORMATION AND DATES AT A GLANCE 
EVENTS DATES 
Online Submission of Application Form 08 February 2026 to 08 March 2026  
(upto 09:00 P.M.) 
Last date of successful transaction of fee 
through Credit/Debit Card/Net-Banking/UPI 
08 March 2026  
(upto 11:50 P.M.) 
Correction in Particulars  10 March 2026 to 12 March 2026 
Announcement of City Intimation To be announced later on the website 
Downloading of Admit Cards from the NTA 
website 
To be announced later on the website 
Date of Examination 03 May 2026 (Sunday) 
Duration of Examination 180 minutes (03 hours) 
Timing of Examination 02:00 PM to 05:00 PM (Indian Standard 
Time) 
Centre of NEET (UG) - 2026 Examination As indicated on Admit Card 
Display of Recorded Responses and Answer 
Keys 
To be announced later on the website 
Website(s) https://nta.ac.in/ 
https://neet.nta.nic.in/ 
Declaration of Result on NTA website To be announced later on the website 
                                                FEE PAYBALE FOR NEET (UG) 2026 
Category of Candidate In India 
(Fee in ₹) 
Outside India 
General ₹ 1700/- ₹ 9500/- 
General-EWS/ OBC-NCL* ₹ 1600/- 
SC/ST/PwBD/PwD/Third Gender ₹ 1000/- 
*OBC-NCL (Other Backward Classes)-NCL (Non-Creamy Layer) as per the Central List of Other 
Backward Classes available on the National Commission for Backward Classes. The candidates 
falling in this list (available on http://www.ncbc.nic.in/) may mention OBC -NCL in the Category 
Column.  
TIMING AND PATTERN OF NEET (UG) 2026 
The pattern for the NEET (UG) - 2026 is as follows: 
 
Subject Type of Questions Duration Number of 
Questions 
Marks 
Physics MCQ 
(Multiple Choice Questions) 
with four options and single 
correct answer/best option. 
02:00 PM to 
05:00 PM 
45 180 
Chemistry 45 180 
Biology (Botany 
& Zoology) 
90 360 
 180 720 
 
Instructions in the Information Bulletin may change /updated based on decisions taken by the NTA 
and other authorities from time to time. Aspirants are, therefore, advised to regularly visit the NTA 
official website at www.nta.ac.in and https://neet.nta.nic.in/ for further updates, instructions, or 
public notices regarding NEET (UG) - 2026. 
 
 
 

===== PDF PAGE 26 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
21 
CHAPTER 4 
 EXAMINATION SCHEME 
1.  SYLLABUS OF THE TEST 
 NMC (National Medical Commission) has notified the syllabus of NEET (UG) - 2026. The 
detailed syllabus (Appendix-III) is available on the official Website(s) of NTA and NMC 
(https://www.nmc.org.in) 
2.  PATTERN OF THE TEST 
The Test pattern of NEET (UG) - 2026 comprises Physics, Chemistry, Biology (Botany & 
Zoology). The question paper will consist of 180 compulsory questions which must be 
attempted by the candidates in 180 minutes.  
 
(As per Letter CDN-20011/289/2024-Cordination-NMC dated 05.12.2025) 
 
The pattern for the NEET (UG) - 2026 is as under : 
 
Subject Type of Questions Duration 
Number of 
Questions Marks 
Physics 
MCQ 
(Multiple Choice Questions) 
with four options and single 
correct answer/best option. 
02:00 PM to 
05:00 PM 
45 180 
Chemistry 45 180 
Biology 
(Botany & 
Zoology) 90 360 
Total 180 720 
 
3 IMPORTANT POINTS TO NOTE: 
 
To answer a question, the candidate needs to choose one option corresponding to the correct 
answer or the most appropriate answer.  Marking will be done as per following criteria : 
 
(i) Correct answer or the most appropriate answer: Four marks (+4) 
(ii) Any incorrect option marked will be given minus one mark (-1).  
(iii) Unanswered: No mark (0). 
 
       While every effort will be made to ensure that each question has one unique answer, in case, it 
is found that a question has more than one option, it will be dealt in following manner: 
 
(i) If more than one option is found to be correct then Four marks (+4) will be awarded 
to only those who have marked any of the correct options.  
(ii) If all options are found to be correct then Four marks (+4) will be awarded to all 
those who have attempted the question.  
(iii) If none of the options is found correct or a Question is found to be wrong or 
a Question is dropped then all candidates who have appeared will be given 
four marks (+4) irrespective of the fact whether the question has been 
attempted or not attempted by the candidate. 
 

===== PDF PAGE 27 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
22 
 
4 MODE OF EXAMINATION 
NEET (UG) – 2026 will be a single day/ single shift  exam in PEN and PAPER mode as was 
conducted in 2025. (As per Letter CDN-20011/289/2024-Cordination-NMC dated 05.12.2025) 
 
5. DURATION OF TEST 
The duration of the test would be three (03) hours. Compensatory time of one hour for 
examination of three hours (03:00 hrs)  duration for PwD/PwBD candidate (having a physical 
limitation to write) will be given  whether such candidate uses the facility of Scribe or not.  
 
6.  MEDIUM OF THE QUESTION PAPERS 
i. NEET (UG) -2026 is being conducted in English, Hindi, Assamese, B engali, 
Gujarati, Kannada, Malayalam, Marathi, Odia, Punjabi, Tamil, Telugu and Urdu  
mediums. 
 
Candidates can opt for a Question Paper in any one of the following 13 mediums: 
 
ii.  Option of medium of Question Paper should be carefully chosen while filling 
in the Application Form. The option once chosen cannot be changed. 
iii. Candidates opting for English would be provided Test Booklet in English 
medium only. 
iv. Candidates opting for Hindi would be provided with a Bilingual Test Booklet in 
English and Hindi medium. 
v. Candidates opting for Regional Languages would be provided Test Booklet in 
English + selected Regional Language medium. (For Example: If a candidate 
opted Tamil (out of 13 languages), the Test Booklet would be provided in English 
+ Tamil). 
vi. In case of any ambiguity in the translation of a question in the test , its English 
version shall be treated as final and the decision of NTA shall be final in this 
regard. 
vii. For the correctness of the questions in all the question papers, the English version 
will be taken as final. 
viii. Candidates qualifying for NEET (UG) – 2026 would be eligible for All India Quota 
and other quotas under the State Governments/Institutes, irrespective of the 
medium of the examination, subject to other eligibility criteria.  
  
Assamese Bengali English Gujarati Hindi Kannada Malayalam 
Marathi Odia Punjabi Tamil Telugu Urdu 

===== PDF PAGE 30 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
25 
CHAPTER 6 
ELIGIBILITY AND QUALIFICATIONS FOR MBBS AND BDS COURSE 
1. ELIGIBILITY TO APPEAR IN NEET (UG) – 2026 
Eligibility for appearing in NEET (UG), as per related Regulations of NMC and DCI are as 
follows: - 
 
As per the Graduate Medical Education Regulation-2023 (Amendment) dated 16.06.2023, 
following amendment with respect to minimum age has been notified in GMER-2023, 
which mandates that: 
i) He/She has completed the age of 17 years as on or before 31st December of the year 
that the candidate shall be appearing for NEET-UG examination. 
ii) Accordingly, the lower age limit shall be as under:    
 
For Candidates of General (UR)/General-EWS born on or before 
31.12.2009 For Candidates of SC/ST/OBC-NCL/PwBD/PwD 
Category 
 
iii) Upper age limit: (As per Letter No. U-11022/2/2022-UGMEB, dated 09 March 2022 
received from National Medical Commission (NMC), Under Graduate Medical 
Education Board (UGMEB) regarding the upper age limit) there is no upper age 
limit. 
(As per Letter No. U-14023/19/NEET(UG Exam)/UGMEB dated 13.01.2026)  
iv)  Indian Citizens/ Overseas Citizens of India (OCI) intending to pursue Undergraduate 
Medical Courses in a foreign Medical/ Dental Institute also need to qualify for NEET 
(UG). 
2. CRITERIA FOR NRI / OCI / FOREIGN NATIONALS 
i) Non-Resident Indians (NRIs), Overseas Citizens of India (OCI), and Foreign Nationals 
are eligible for admission in Medical /Dental Colleges subject to rules and regulations 
framed by the respective State Governments, Institutions, and the Government of 
India, as the case may be. The NRI and OCI Applicants/Candidates have to upload a 
Certificate from the concerned Indian Diplomatic Mission in the country of their 
residence in support of their claim as an NRI/OCI Candidate, along with their online 
Application Form for NEET (UG) - 2026 and retain the original of such document for 
producing it at the time of Counselling / Admission to the Courses covered under NEET 
(UG). Similarly, a foreign applicant for NEET (UG) 2026 shall also upload Documentary 
Proof (e.g. relevant pages of a valid passport or a Certificate from the Competent 
Authority in the country of his/her Nationality regarding his/her citizenship status) in 
support of his/her Nationality, along with online Application Form. The format of 
Embassy Certif icate and Citizenship Certificate or any Documentary proof of 
Citizenship are given in Appendix –  VI and Appendix – VII. Foreign nationals may 
confirm their eligibility from the competent state authorities and counselling authorities, 
as the case may be.  

===== PDF PAGE 31 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
26 
ii) Eligibility of OCI cardholders for NEET (UG):  
a) Indian Nationals, Non-Resident Indians (NRIs), Overseas Citizen of India (OCI), 
Persons with Indian Origin and Foreign Nationals are eligible for admission in 
Medical/Dental/Ayurveda/Siddha/Unani/ Homoeopathy Colleges subject to the 
rules and regulations framed by respective State Governments, Institutions and 
The Government of India, as the case may be. 
b) In compliance of the Hon’ble Supreme Court Order dated 03.02.2023 in WP No. 
891 of 2021, OCI will be entitled to the rights and privileges which had been 
conferred on them earlier to the notification dated 04.03.2021. 
3. QUALIFICATIONS AND QUALIFYING EXAMINATION CODES 
As per approval conveyed by the NMC (As per  Letter CDN-20011/289/2024-Cordination-NMC dated 
05.12.2025 and Letter U -14023/19/NEET(UG Exam)/UGMEB dated 13.01.2026 and Email vide 
NMC UGSection dated 28.01.2026) 
To be eligible for NEET (UG) – 2026, candidates need to refer to the following table for 
qualifying examination criteria. 
CODE: 01  
 
A candidate who is appearing in the qualifying examination, whose 12th result 
is awaited, may apply and appear in the test but he/she shall not be eligible 
for admission to the Undergraduate Medical Courses  if he/she does not 
pass the qualifying examination at the time of first round of Counseling.  
 
Candidates who have undertaken study of the requisite subjects i.e. Physics, 
Chemistry, Biology / Biotechnology along with English even as additional 
subjects after passing Class 12th from duly recognized boards by the 
concerned Govt. such candidates shall be permitted to appear in NEET -UG 
Test and resultantly also be eligible for grant of Eligibility Certificate as per 
Public Notice dated 22.11.2023 .  However, their candidature will be 
considered only if they provide documentary evidence of having passed the 
qualifying Examination with the required subjects. 
  
                                                                              OR 
CODE: 02  
 
The Higher/Senior Secondary Examination or the Indian School Certificate 
Examination which is equivalent to class 12 Higher/Senior Secondary 
Examination after a period of 12 years of study, the study of the requisite 
subjects i.e. Physics, Chemistry, Biology / Biotechnology along with English 
even as additional subjects after passing Class 12th from duly recognized 
boards by the concerned Govt. (which shall include practical tests in these 
subjects) and Mathematics or any other elective subject with English at a level 
not less than the core course for English as prescribed by the National Council 
of Educational Research and Training after the int roduction of the 10+2+3 
educational structure as recommended by the National Committee on 
Education.  
 
Public Notice dated 22.11.2023 (Para -7), consequent to the introduction of 
NEP and various legal issues, further adds that:  The National Medical 
Commission in its meeting held on 14.06.2023 after detailed deliberations 
while taking into consideration the NEP, which permits great extent of 
flexibility in the study of various subjects in Class 12th, decided that the 
previous approach of the erstwhile Medical Council of India needs to be 

===== PDF PAGE 32 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
27 
revisited by permitting candidates to undertaken study of the requisite 
subjects (Physics, Chemistry, Biology / Biotechnology alongwith English) 
even as additional subjects after passing Class 12 th from boards duly 
recognized  by the concerned Govt. Such candidates shall be permitted to 
appear in NEET-UG Test and resultantly also be eligible for grant of Eligibility 
Certificate. 
 
If the institute has to consider an examination of an Indian University or of a 
foreign/university to be equivalent to the Class 12 under intermediate science 
examination, the candidates shall have to produce a certificate from the 
concerned Indian Univers ity/Association of Indian Universities to the effect 
that the examination passed by him/her is considered to be equivalent to the 
class 12 under intermediate science examination. 
                                                                          OR 
CODE: 03  
 
The Intermediate/Pre -degree Examination in Science of an Indian 
University/Board or other recognized examining body with Physics, 
Chemistry, Biology /Biotechnology (which shall include practical test in 
these subjects) and also English as a compulsory subject. 
                                                                         OR 
CODE: 04  
 
The Pre-professional/Pre-medical Examination with Physics, Chemistry, 
Biology/Biotechnology, and English after passing either the Higher 
Secondary Examination or the Pre -University or an equivalent 
examination. The Pre-professional/Pre-medical examination shall include 
practical tests in these subjects and also English as a compulsory subject. 
                                                                        OR 
CODE: 05  
 
The first year of the three years’ degree course of a recognized University 
with Physics, Chemistry, and Biology/Biotechnology including practical 
tests in these subjects provided the examination is a University 
Examination and the candidate has passed the  earlier qualifying 
examination with Physics, Chemistry, Biology/ Biotechnology with English 
at a level not less than a core course. 
                                                                       OR 
CODE: 06  
 
B.Sc. Examination of an Indian University provided that he/she has 
passed the B.Sc. Examination with not less than two of the subjects 
Physics, Chemistry, Biology (Botany, Zoology)/Biotechnology and further 
that he/ she has passed the earlier qualifying ex amination with Physics, 
Chemistry, Biology, and English.  
                                                                       OR 
CODE: 07 
 
Any other examination which in scope and standard (Last 02 years of 
10+2 Study comprising of Physics, Chemistry and Biology/Biotechnology; 
which shall include practical test in these subjects) is found to be 
equivalent to the Intermediate Science Examinati on of an Indian 
University/Board, taking Physics, Chemistry and Biology/Biotechnology 
including practical tests in each of these subjects and English. 
 
  

===== PDF PAGE 34 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
29 
CHAPTER 7 
 
COUNSELLING AND RESERVATION FOR ADMISSION TO MBBS, BAMS, BUMS, BSMS, 
BHMS, BDS AND B.SC. NURSING COURSES 
1. ADMISSION PROCEDURE 
Admissions to all seats of Undergraduate Medical / Dental Courses will be 
done through NEET (UG) - 2026.  
 
A. The following are the seats available under different quotas:  
• All India Quota Seats 
• State Government Quota Seats 
• Seats available for admission in  Central Institutions/Universities/Deemed 
Universities 
• State/Self-financed merit list /NRI Quota Seats in Private Medical / Dental 
Colleges or any Private University  
• Central Pool Quota Seats 
• All seats including NRI Quota as well as “self-financed merit list”, are in private 
unaided/aided minority / non-minority medical colleges. 
• Seats available for admission in AIIMS Institutes across India/JIPMER. 
• The Counselling for successful candidates for Seats under 15% All India Quota 
and 100% including 85% State quota seats of Central Institutions (ABVIMS & 
RML Hospital/VMMC & Safdarjung Hospital/ESIC)/ Central Universities 
(including DU/ BHU /AMU)/ AIIMS/ JI PMER and Deemed Universities, will be 
conducted by the MCC/DGHS for Undergraduate Medical / Dental Courses. 
MCC only does the registration for AFMC and forwards the data of registered 
Candidates to AFMC Authorities for the admission process. DU/BHU and other 
Universities may use the score for any other relevant courses being 
offered by them. 
B. The counselling for admission to the seats under the control of State Governments/ 
UT Administrations / State Universities/ Institutions shall be conducted by the 
designated authorities of the State Governments as per the notifications issued 
separately by the authorities concerned. 
 
C. The Result of NEET (UG) - 2026 may be utilized by other Entities of Central and 
State Governments, in accordance with their respective eligibility criteria / other 
norms /applicable regulations/guidelines/rules. The result data will also be utilized 
for B.Sc. (H) Nursing courses in accordance with their respective eligibility criteria / 
other norms /applicable regulations/guidelines/ rules. The NEET (UG) - 2026 data 
will also be used for admissions to BVSc & AH courses under the 15% quota of VCI 
in recognized Veterinary Colleges. However, the Council has to approach the MCC 
of DGHS, MoHFW in order to obtain the said data of results. 
 
Note: Military Nursing Service (M NS) aspirants seeking admission to B.Sc 
Nursing Course being conducted at Armed Forces Medical Service Hospitals 

===== PDF PAGE 37 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
32 
4. RESERVATION POLICY FOR ADMISSION TO MBBS /BDS/B.SC. NURSING 
CONDUCTED BY MCC/DGHS 
1) Indian nationals belonging to certain categories are admitted under the seats 
reserved for them in accordance with the rules prescribed by the Government of 
India. The categories and the extent of reservation are as follows: 
 
➢ General category belonging to Economically Weaker Section (GEN- EWS) – 10% 
of seats in every course. The benefit of reservation will be given only to those General 
category candidates who satisfy the conditions given in the OM No. 20013/01/2018-
BCII dated 17 January 2019,  issued by the Ministry of Social Justice and 
Empowerment. The criteria for GEN-EWS will be as per the prevailing norms and/or 
notifications of the Government of India. 
 
➢ Other Backward Classes belonging to the Non -Creamy Layer (OBC- NCL) – 27% of 
seats in every course. 
 
i. OBC-NCL should be listed in the current updated central list of OBC -NCL 
(http://www.ncbc.nic.in). 
ii. OBC-NCL present in the State list but not covered in the central list of OBC -
NCL (as per the list in http://www.ncbc.nic.in) are NOT eligible to claim the 
reservation. 
iii. The criteria for OBC-NCL will be as per the notification of the Government of 
India. 
iv. Candidates belonging to the creamy layer of OBC are NOT entitled to 
reservation. Such candidates are treated as belonging to the general 
(GEN), i.e. unreserved category, and they will be eligible only for the 
GEN seats – the seats for which all candidates are eligible. 
➢ Scheduled Caste (SC) – 15% of seats in every course. 
➢ Scheduled Tribe (ST) – 7.5% of seats in every course. 
➢ Persons with Benchmark Disability (PwBD) – 5% seats in each of GEN, GEN -
EWS, OBC-NCL, SC, and ST category seats (Horizontal reservation). 
 
i. Candidates who want to avail the benefits of PwBD reservation in admission 
to Undergraduate Courses  will be governed as per NMC guidelines 
(Appendix-VI) and subsequent amendments from time to time. 
 
Reservation in State Quota Seats /Universities/Institutions /Private Medical 
Colleges under State Governments : In case of seats filled by the State 
Medical Colleges/Universities/Institutions /Private Medical Colleges under 
State Quota Seats, the reservation policy of the concerned State 
Government shall apply. 
 
ii. For Candidates claiming the GEN-EWS category 
Candidate should possess valid GEN-EWS certificate (who satisfy the conditions 
given in the OM No. 20013/01/2018-BC-II dated 17 January 2019,  issued by 
the Ministry of Social Justice and Empowerment) in consonance with the latest 

===== PDF PAGE 44 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
39 
CHAPTER 8 
MERIT LIST AND QUALIFYING CRITERIA 
1. QUALIFYING CRITERIA 
i. The NTA will prepare the Merit List/All India Rank (AIR) as per Qualifying/eligibility criteria 
and other norms as well as the relevant regulations/guidelines of NMC/DGHS/MCC/DCI 
and Ministry of AYUSH/NCISM/NCH/CCH/AACCC, as the case may be. The details 
received from the respective competent authority(ies) will be displayed on the NTA 
website (https://neet.nta.nic.in/) in due course of time. 
ii. The eligibility criteria for admission to Undergraduate Medical Courses are as follows: 
a. In order to be eligible for admission to Undergraduate Medical Courses for a 
particular academic year in case of General, General-EWS, it shall be necessary for 
a candidate to obtain a minimum of marks at the 50th percentile in National Eligibility 
Cum Entrance Test to Undergraduate Medical Courses held for the said academic 
year. However, in respect of candidates belonging to Scheduled Castes, Scheduled 
Tribes, Other Backward Classes, the minimum marks shall be at the 40th percentile. 
In respect of cand idates with Benchmark, Disabilities specified under the Rights of 
Persons with Disabilities Act, 2016, the minimum marks shall be at 45th percentile for 
Unreserved Category & GEN -EWS Category candidates and 40th percentile for 
SC/ST/OBC-NCL candidates. The percentile shall be determined on the basis of the 
highest marks secured in the All India common merit list in the National Eligibility Cum 
Entrance Test for admission to Undergraduate Medical Courses. 
b. Provided when a sufficient number of candidates in the respective categories fail 
to secure minimum marks as prescribed in National Eligibility Cum Entrance Test held 
for any academic year for admission to Undergraduate Medical Courses, the Central 
Government in consultation with the National Medical Commission and Dental 
Council of India, National Commission for Indian System of Medicines and National 
Commission of Homeopathy and any other regulatory body may at its discretion lower 
the minimum marks re quired for admission to Undergraduate Medical Courses for 
candidates belonging to respective categories and marks so lowered by the Central 
Government shall be applicable for the said academic year only. 
c. For admission in BUMS (Bachelor of Unani Medicine and Surgery) Course, the 
candidate must have passed the 10th standard with Urdu or Arabic or Persian 
language as a subject, or clear the test of Urdu of 10th Standard (wherever there is 
provision to conduct  of such test) in the entrance examination conducted by the 
University or Board or registered Society or Association authorized by the 
Government to conduct such examination. For admission in the BSMS (Bachelor of 
Sidhha Medicine and Surgery) course, the Candidate must have passed Tamil as one 
of the subjects in the 10th Standard/in Higher Secondary course or Candidates shall 
have to study Tamil as a subject during the First Professional course. 
d. Provided that a candidate who has appeared in the qualifying examination, the 
result of which has not been declared, may be provisionally permitted to take up the 
competitive entrance examination and in case of selection for admission to the 
Undergraduate Medical Courses, he/she shall not be admitted to that course until 
he/she fulfills the eligibility criteria as specified above.  For details, candidates may 
refer to the Graduate Medical Education Regulations,  2023 and relevant notifications 
issued by NMC on time to time and BDS Course Regulations, 2007, the Indian 
Medicine Central Council (Minimum Standards of Education in Indian Medicine) 
Regulation, and the Homoeopathy (Degree Course) Regulations, 1983. 

===== PDF PAGE 45 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
40 
e. The criteria for minimum qualifying marks to be eligible for admission to MBBS 
courses shall also be applicable to concerned INIs. 
 
iii)  A list of the successful candidates in order of All India Rank based on the marks 
obtained in the National Eligibility Cum Entrance Test (NEET) UG – 2026 will be 
prepared by the NTA.  
 
2. THE INTER-SE-MERIT OF CANDIDATES FOR TIE-BREAKING 
In case of two or more candidates obtain ing equal marks/percentile scores in the NEET (UG) - 
2026, the inter-se-merit shall be determined as follows: 
a. Candidate obtaining higher marks/percentile score in Biology (Botany & Zoology) in 
the Test, followed by, 
b. Candidate obtaining higher marks/percentile score in Chemistry in the Test, followed 
by, 
c. Candidate obtaining higher marks/percentile score in Physics in the Test, followed by, 
d. Candidate with less proportion of the number of attempted incorrect answers and 
correct answers in all the subjects in the Test, 
e. Candidate with less proportion of number of attempted incorrect answers and correct 
answers in Biology (Botany & Zoology) in the Test, followed by 
f. Candidate with less proportion of number of attempted incorrect answers and correct 
answers in Chemistry in the Test, followed by 
g. Candidate with less proportion of number of attempted incorrect answers and correct 
answers in Physics in the Test, followed by 
h. In case, a-g criteria are exhausted and tie still persists, it will be resolved through a 
random process with the guidance of an independent expert committee. 
(As per  Public Notice dated 13.06.2023 issued by UGMEB/NMC and Email vide NMC 
UGSection dated 28.01.2026) 
 
3.  MERIT LIST FOR COUNSELLING UNDER 15% ALL INDIA QUOTA 
 
The merit list of the eligible and successful candidates who have opted for 15% of All India quota 
seats will be prepared by the NTA on the basis of marks obtained in the NEET (UG) - 2026.  The 
list of successful candidates shall be forwarded to the Directorate General of Health Services 
(MCC), Ministry of Health and Family Welfare, Government of India, and National 
Commission for Indian System of Medicine (NCISM) and National Commission for 
Homoeopathy (NCH), Ministry of AYUSH, Govt. of India for the purpose of allotment of seats 
by Online Counselling to 15% All India Quota Seats. 
 
4.  MERIT LIST FOR SEATS OTHER THAN 15% ALL INDIA QUOTA 
 
a. NTA will provide All India Rank and Result will be shared with the DGHS, Ministry of Health 
and Family Welfare, Govt of India and Ministry of AYUSH, Govt. of India along with National 
Commission for Indian System of Medicine (NCISM) and National Commission for 
Homoeopathy (NCH) to provide the same to the counselling authorities.  
 
b. Counselling authorities will invite applications for Counselling. 
 
c. The counselling authorities will draw a merit list of the candidates based on All India Rank 
in the respective categories declared by the candidates at the time of applying for 
admission/counselling as per State applicable rules. 
  

===== PDF PAGE 49 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
44 
CHAPTER 10 
ADMIT CARD 
1. The Admit Card is issued provisionally to the candidates, subject to the fulfillment of the eligibility 
conditions. 
2. The candidate has to download the Admit Card from the NTA website ( https://neet.nta.nic.in/) 
and appear for the Examination at the given Centre on the Date and timing as indicated in their 
Admit Card. 
3. No candidate will be allowed to appear at the Examination Centre, on the Date and Timing other 
than that allotted to him/her in his / her Admit Card.  
4. In case a candidate is unable to download his/ her Admit Card from the website, he or she may 
approach the Help Line between 10:00 AM to 05.00 PM or write an email to NTA at 
neetug2026@nta.ac.in. 
5. The candidates are advised to read the instructions given in this Information Bulletin as 
well as on the Admit Card carefully and follow them scrupulously during the conduct of 
the examination.  
6. In case of any discrepancy in the particulars of the candidate or his/her photograph and 
signatures shown in the Admit Card and Confirmation Page, the candidate may immediately 
approach the Help Line between 10:00 AM and 5:00 PM. In such cases, candidates would 
appear in the Examination with the already downloaded Admit Card. However, NTA will 
take necessary action to make corrections in the record later. 
 
 
Note: 
a. The candidate may note that Admit Card will not be sent by post. 
b. In no case, the duplicate Admit Card for NEET (UG) -2026 would be issued at the 
Examination Centres. 
c. The candidate must not mutilate the Admit Card or change any entry made therein. 
d. Candidates are advised to preserve their Admit Card in good condition for future 
reference. 
e. No Admit Card shall be issued to the candidates whose Applications are found to be 
incomplete for any reasons (including indistinct/ doubtful photographs/unsigned 
Applications) or who do not fulfill the eligibility criteria for the examination.  
f. Issue of Admit Card, however, shall not necessarily mean acceptance of eligibility 
which shall be further scrutinized at subsequent stages of the admission process 
 
 
 
 
  

===== PDF PAGE 50 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
45 
CHAPTER 11 
BARRED ITEMS AND DRESS CODE 
1.  BARRED ITEMS 
i) The candidates will be subjected to extensive and compulsory frisking before entering the 
Examination Centre with the help of highly sensitive metal detectors. The candidates are not 
allowed to carry the following items inside the Examination Centre under any circumstances.  
a) Any item like textual material (printed or written), bits of papers, Geometry/Pencil 
Box, Plastic Pouch, Calculator, Pen, Scale, Writing Pad, Pen Drives, Eraser, 
Calculator, Log Table, Electronic Pen/Scanner, etc. 
b) Any communication device like Mobile Phone, Bluetooth, Earphones, 
Microphone, Pager, Health Band, etc. 
c) Other items like Wallet, Goggles, Handbags, Belt, Cap, etc. 
d) Any Watch/Wristwatch, Bracelet, Camera, etc. 
e) Any ornaments/metallic items. 
f) Any food items opened or packed, water bottle, etc. 
g) Any other item which could be used for unfair means, by hiding communication 
devices like a microchip, camera, Bluetooth device, etc. 
ii)  No arrangement will be made at the Centres for keeping any articles/items belonging to the 
candidates. 
iii) The candidates wearing articles or objects of faith (customary/ cultural/ religious) should 
report at the examination centre at least two hours before the last reporting time so that 
there is enough time for proper frisking without any inconvenience to the  candidate while 
maintaining the sanctity of the examination. If upon screening, it is discovered that any 
candidate is actually carrying a suspected device within such item of faith, he/ she may be 
asked not to take it into the examination hall.  
2. DRESS CODE 
i. The candidates are instructed to follow the following dress code while appearing for NEET 
(UG) –2026: 
a. Heavy clothes and/or long sleeves are not p referable. However, in case, 
candidates come in cultural/ customary dress at the Examination Centre, they 
should report at least an hour before the last reporting time i.e. 12.30 PM so that 
there is enough time for proper frisking without any inconvenience to the 
candidate while maintaining the sanctity of the examination. 
b. Slippers, sandals with low heels are preferable.  
c. In case of any deviation required due to unavoidable (medical, etc.) 
circumstances, specific approval of NTA must be taken before the Admit 
Cards are issued.  
ii. It is desired that the candidates follow instructions issued by the NTA strictly. This will help 
NTA in the fair conduct of the examination.   
iii. The candidates will be subjected to extensive and compulsory frisking before entering the 
Examination Centre with the help of highly sensitive metal detectors.  They may also 
undergo various other identity verification checks, such as Biometric, Face Authe ntication, 
videography etc.  
Note:    NTA believes in the sanctity and fairness of conducting the examination, however, 
it also believes in the sensitivity involved in frisking (girl) candidates and will 
issue comprehensive instructions accordingly to the staff and other officials at 
the Examination Centres. The frisking of the female candidates will be done inside 
a closed enclosure by female staff only. 

===== PDF PAGE 52 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
47 
CHAPTER 13 
INSTRUCTIONS TO BE FOLLOWED IN THE EXAMINATION HALL 
 
1. The Examination Centre will be opened three (03) hours before the commencement of the 
test. No candidate shall be allowed to enter the Examination Centre after 1:30 PM. Therefore, 
candidates must ensure that they leave home well in advance considering all facts like traffic, 
location of the Centre, weather conditions, etc. Candidates are expected to take their seats 
immediately after the opening of the Examination Hall. 
* (06:00 PM for eligible PwD/PwBD candidates) 
 
2. The candidate must show, on-demand, the Admit Card for admission in the Examination Hall. 
A candidate who does not possess a valid Admit Card shall not be allowed to enter the 
Examination Hall by the Centre Superintendent.  
3. A seat with a roll number will be allotted to each candidate. Candidates must find out and 
occupy their allotted seats. If a candidate is found appearing in the Examination from a seat 
or room other than the allotted one, the candidature shall be cancelled. 
4. During the examination time, the Invigilator will check Admit Card of the candidates to ascertain 
the identity of each candidate. The Invigilators will also put their own signature in the place 
provided in the Answer Sheet and on the Attendance Sheet. 
5. A candidate who comes after 01:30 PM shall not be permitted to enter the Examination Centre 
under any circumstances. 
6. Candidates must bring ONLY the following documents on the day of examination at the 
test centre. Candidates who will not bring these will not be allowed to sit in the 
examination. 
• A printed copy of Admit Card downloaded from NTA website with passport size 
photograph (same as uploaded on the Application form pasted on it). 
• One passport size photograph (same as uploaded on the Online Application Form) for 
pasting on the specific space in the Attendance Sheet at Centre during NEET (UG) - 
2026 Examination. 
• One Post Card Size (4”X6”) color photograph with white background should be 
pasted on the Proforma downloaded with the Admit Card.  
• Any one of the authorized photo IDs (must be original and valid like PAN card/Driving 
License/Voter ID/Passport/Aadhaar Card /DigiLocker, APAAR ID. 
• Certificate of physical limitation to write and/or PwBD certificate issued by the Competent 
Authority, if claiming the relaxation under PwBD category. 
 
Date of Examination 03 May 2026 (Sunday) 
• Timing and Duration of Examination 
02.00 PM to 05.00 PM (Indian Standard 
Time) 
(3 hours) 
• Reporting/Entry time at Centre 11:00 AM 
• Last Entry to the Examination Centre 01.30 PM 
• Announcement of Important Instructions 
and Checking of Admit Cards by the 
Invigilator 
01.30 PM to 01.45 PM 
• Distribution of Test Booklet by the 
Invigilator 01.45 PM 
• Writing of particulars on the Test Booklet 
by the Candidate 01.50 PM 
• Test Commences 02.00 PM 
• Test Concludes 05.00 PM* 

===== PDF PAGE 53 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
48 
7. Candidates are not allowed to bring any barred item or any item which could be used for 
Unfair practices. Possession of any such article with the candidates inside the Centre 
premises will attract the penalties of unfair practices as per Public Examinations (Prevention 
of Unfair Means) Act, 2024. 
8. Candidates are advised in their own interest not to bring any of the barred items to the venue 
of the examination as arrangements for safekeeping will not be made and candidates found 
in possession of these items will not be allowed to enter the Examination Centre.  
9. No candidate will leave his/her seat or the Examination Room/Hall until the Test concludes 
as per the schedule. Candidates should not leave the Room/Hall without handing over their 
OMR Sheets to the invigilator on duty.  
10. Smoking in the examination centre and nearby is strictly prohibited.  
11. Water Bottles, Tea, coffee, cold drinks or snacks, etc. are not allowed to be taken by the 
candidates into the examination centre. Candidates suffering from diabetes are allowed to 
carry into the examination hall the eatables (with prior intimation) like sugar tablets/fruits (like 
banana/apple/orange) and transparent water bottles. However, they will not be allowed to 
carry packed foods like chocolate/ candy/sandwich, etc. 
12. The Test will start exactly at the time mentioned in the Admit Card and an announcement to 
this effect will be made by the Invigilator.  
13. Before the start of the Examination, important instructions will be communicated to the 
candidates by the Invigilator for strict compliance by the candidates. 
14. A  signal will be given at the beginning of the examination and at half-time. A signal will also 
be given before the closing time when the candidate must stop marking the responses. 
15. The candidate must sign twice on the Attendance Sheet at the specified place, the first time 
immediately after the commencement of the examination and the second time while handing 
over the Answer Sheet to the Invigilator (This time indicated on the Attend ance 
Sheets/Answer Sheets is in no way reflection of the actual time of distribution of the question 
papers and the receipt of Answer Sheets packed by the invigilator due to operational 
aspects). The candidates are also required to put the Thumb impression in the space 
provided on the Attendance Sheet. 
16. The candidate will check and ensure that the Test Booklet contains as many pages as are 
written on the top of the cover page. 
17. For those who are unable to appear on the scheduled date of the test for any reason, a re -
test shall not be held by the NTA under any circumstances. 
18. The candidates, suffering from Diabetes, may be taken care of at the Centre as per the 
instructions issued by NTA.  
19. The conduct of the NEET (UG) - 2026 Examination would be videographed. The candidates 
are required to keep their heads in an upright position and face the camera during the 
videography so that their identity can be clearly established. The candidates should agree to 
the videography during the examination. 

===== PDF PAGE 54 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
49 
CHAPTER 14 
UNFAIR MEANS PRACTICES AND BREACH OF EXAMINATION RULES 
 
1. Definition 
Unfair means practice is an activity that allows a candidate to gain an unfair advantage over 
other candidates. It includes, but is not limited to: 
 
a. Being in possession of any item or article which has been prohibited or can be used 
for unfair practices including any stationery item, communication device, accessories, 
eatables, ornaments, or any other material or information relevant or not relevant to  
the examination in the paper concerned.  
b. Using someone to write the examination (impersonation) or preparing material for 
copying; 
c. Breaching examination rules or any direction issued by NTA in connection with the 
conduct of the NEET (UG) - 2026 examination from time to time. 
d. Assisting other candidates to engage in malpractices, giving or receiving assistance 
directly or indirectly of any kind or attempting to do so; 
e. Writing questions or answers on any material other than the answer sheet given by 
the Centre Superintendent for writing answers. 
f. Tearing/Defacing of filled OMR Sheet, any page of the test booklet, etc.  
g. Contacting or communicating or trying to do so with any person, other than the 
Examination Staff, during the examination time in the Examination Centre. 
h. Taking away the answer sheet (Original OMR/Office Copy of OMR) out of the 
examination hall/room. 
i. Smuggling out of Question Paper or its part or smuggling out answer sheet or part 
thereof.  
j. Threatening any of the officials connected with the conduct of the examination or 
threatening any of the candidates. 
k. Using or attempting to use any other undesirable method or means in connection with 
the examination. 
l. Manipulation and fabrication of online documents viz. admit card, rank letter, self -
declaration, etc. 
m. Forceful entry/exit in/from Examination Centre/Hall. 
n. Use or attempted use of any electronic device after entering the Examination Centre; 
o. Affixing/uploading of wrong/morphed photographs on the application form/admit 
card/proforma. 
p. Erasing or obliterating any information printed on the OMR Answer Sheet. 
q. Providing incorrect information and/or overwriting of the Roll No./ Test Booklet No. / 
own Name of the Candidate / Father’s Name / Mother’s Name / own Signature, on 
the OMR Answer Sheet. 
r. Making fake claims by manipulating the responses in the OMR sheet by/on tampering 
it in any way whatsoever, uploaded on the website for the challenge before or after 
the declaration of the result. 
s. Creating obstacles in smooth and fair conduct of the examination.  
t. Any other malpractices declared as Unfair means by the NTA. 
u. Any other unfair means practice covered under Clause 3 of Chapter II under Public 
Examinations (Prevention of Unfair Means) Act, 2024. 

===== PDF PAGE 56 =====

           INFORMATION BULLETIN NEET (UG)-2026 
 
51 
CHAPTER 15 
POST EXAMINATION ACTIVITIES AND DECLARATION OF RESULT 
1. Display of OMR sheets and responses on the website and challenging the grading of 
questions on OMR 
i. After the conduct of the examination, NTA will display the scanned images of OMR Answer 
Sheets and recorded responses by the machine, of all candidates on the website 
(https://neet.nta.nic.in/). The exact date of display of scanned images of OMR Answer Sheets 
shall be communicated after the examination on the NTA website.  
 
ii. Applicants will be given an opportunity to submit representation against the OMR grading by 
paying a non-refundable processing fee of ₹ 200/- per question challenged.  
 
iii. Representations made by the candidates against the OMR grading will be verified by the 
NTA from the actual record and the same will be updated in the data if challenges are found 
to be correct. However, no intimation in this regard will be sent to an individual candidate.  
 
iv. Applicants are advised to visit the website https://neet.nta.nic.in/ for viewing and downloading 
the image of the OMR Answer Sheet by the candidates. 
 
2. DISPLAY OF ANSWER KEY FOR THE CHALLENGE 
i. The NTA will display the Provisional Answer Key of the questions, giving an opportunity to 
the candidates to challenge, in case of any doubt in the answer key published on the website 
https://neet.nta.nic.in/. For the exact date of display of the Answer Key, candidates may 
regularly check updates on the NTA website after the examination.   
ii. Candidates will be given an opportunity to make an online challenge against the provisional 
Answer Key by paying a non-refundable processing fee of ₹ 200/- per answer challenged, 
within a specified period as indicated in the Public Notice. 
iii. Challenges made by the candidates will be verified by the NTA with the help of a panel 
of subject experts.  If the challenge of any candidate is found correct, the Answer Key 
will be revised and applied in the response of all the candidates accordingly.  B ased 
on the revised Final Answer Key, the result will be prepared and declared . No 
individual candidate will be informed about the acceptance/non-acceptance of his/her 
challenge.  
iv. The key finalized after the challenges will be treated as final and will be displayed on 
NTA website before declaration of result.   
 
3. DECLARATION OF RESULT 
i. The National Testing Agency will evaluate the Answer Sheets using standard procedure and 
the result will be displayed on the website: https://neet.nta.nic.in/ and thereafter candidates 
may download their respective Score Cards. 
 
ii. The NTA will prepare the Merit List/ All India Rank (AIR) as per Qualifying Criteria and other 
norms as mentioned in Chapter 14 of this Bulletin as well as the relevant regulations/ 
guidelines of NMC/DGHS/MCC and Ministry of AYUSH / NCISM /NCH/CCH/AACCC, as the 
case may be. All Candidates appearing in NEET (UG) - 2026 must regularly check updates 
on the website of NTA ( https://neet.nta.nic.in/); MoH&FW(https://www.mohfw.gov.in/ ); 
AYUSH Ministry ( www.ayush.gov.in); DGHS( https://dghs.gov.in/); Medical Counselling 
Committee (https://mcc.nic.in/UGCounselling); (Admission Central Counselling Committee 
of Ministry of AYUSH (https://aaccc.gov.in/) and other concerned Authorities of participating 
States / Universities / Institutions, till the conclusion of the final round of Counselling. 
  
